非一般的時代
非一般的崇拜
歡迎大家來到我們的週六崇拜
由2018年1月開始
我們一直在研讀《馬可福音》
到現在已經有兩年多的時間
我們講到的系列總題是《非凡的見證》
不是因爲馬可是一個非凡的作者
而是因爲主耶穌基督是一個非凡的救主
《馬可福音》是一本怎樣的書呢
德國聖經學者馬汀·凱勒曾經這樣介紹過《馬可福音》
他說《馬可福音》基本上就是一個耶穌受難復活的故事前面
加了一個延伸拉長了的引言
A Passion Narrative with an Extended Introduction
馬可用了十章的聖經
講述了耶穌三年的事工
接着去到第十一章
第十一章我們先進入耶穌最後的一週
而那一週很長
由第十一章一直延伸到第十六章
三年用十章的聖經
最後一週七天用了六章的聖經
在《馬可福音》第十一章和第十二章裏面
記載了耶穌在聖殿裏面
最後一週裏面的聖殿爭霸有七個回合
之前如果你有來周圍崇拜或者在網上有聽過
你知道我們已經講了第一第二第三第四第五個回合
題目分別是愛子的權柄
邪惡的緣故
凱撒的銀貴 復活的上帝和最大的誡命
今天我們要講的是第六個回合
講到的經文只有三節
《馬可福音》第十二章第35至37節
講到的題目是大衛的後裔
如果你前兩個星期有在這裏
你應該記得
其實聖殿的車輪戰去到第四個回合
已經是塵埃落定
去到第四個回合的時候
已經有一羣人連續出場
包括有祭司長、文士、長老
法利塞人、希律黨人、撒度戈人
他們先後出場
統統被耶穌擊敗
然而去到聖殿爭霸的第五個回合
之所以還可以繼續是因爲其中有一個文士
文士已經輸了
有一個文士有一個律法師他不認輸
於是他再來挑戰多耶穌一次
於是給了我們第五個回合
另一方面耶穌又繼續做祂的天國反擊戰
到他們問完祂的問題
現在到耶穌去問祂們一些難題
成爲了我們的第六回合
如果你有留心聽前面四個回合
你會發現耶穌的回答
如何說呢?
祂可以說是玄妙非常
內藏暗格
天外有天
動中有動
祂不是單單回答去擊退少少的敵人
祂的回答很有力
祂擊退了祂所有的強敵異議
在祂的回答當中祂更加要做一件事
那就是展示Unboxing
有沒有看YouTube的Unboxing
祂要將天國展示出來
將上帝救恩的計劃
一步一步一層一層地展示在我們的面前
我不知道你們是否記得在第一個回合當中
第一個回合那些人問祂
祂說你匠匠什麼的權柄來做這些事
來搞我們這個聖殿
耶穌很有趣
祂沒有行一個神蹟
我匠匠什麼權柄去看
沒有一拳打碎他們
然後就說我憑着這個拳頭
祂不是這麼說
祂問他們一個問題
祂說
約翰的洗禮是從天上來還是從人間來
祂問他們一個問題
祂想他們思想在約翰河受洗
那時候天上來的聲音
天上來的什麼聲音
你是我的愛子
我喜歡你
如果你之前有聽我講
這句話很有趣
因爲這句話包含了兩段舊約的聖經
一個是詩篇第二篇
另一個是以恰恰書第42章
耶穌是誰
耶穌用那句話展示祂的身份
耶穌說這是我的愛子
詩篇第二篇
耶穌是詩篇第二篇裏面的應許的君王
但是耶穌還有
我喜愛你
是以恰恰書第42章
耶穌又是以恰恰書第42章至53章裏面
受苦的僕人
耶穌是誰
祂是上帝揀選的君王
祂又是上帝揀選受苦的僕人
更有趣的是第一個回合出場的人有
祭司長、民事長老
是他們第一次共同的出場
但是這個第一次共同的出場
之前在《馬可福音》第8章31節
《馬可福音》8:31
裏面已經預言了有一天
人子要受許多的苦
是被誰
是被長老、被祭司長和民事
耶穌已經預言了這件事
於是在祂的回答當中
祂在展示將要發生的事情
接着在第二個回合
邪惡的緣故里面
耶穌帶我們回到以恰恰書第5章
你大概忘記了
但祂其實帶我們回到《舊約聖經》裏面
一個很美麗的葡萄園的比喻
卻又是一個噩夢
是一個很恐怖的夢
耶穌將葡萄園的比喻
重新改編、重寫
接着祂結束的時候
祂引用詩篇第118篇作爲總結
祂怎樣說?
祂說「將人所棄的石頭
以作了房角石的頭塊石頭
這是主所造的
在我們眼中看爲奇妙」
耶穌是誰?
耶穌是那個原主上帝的愛子
耶穌是被凋棄的石頭
耶穌是被凋棄了
卻又被上帝揀選回來
第三天從死裏復活
建成了永恆聖殿的房角的頭塊石頭
你看祂每一個故事
祂在講一些關於祂自己的東西
這是第二個回合
第三個回合
凱撒的銀幣
耶穌再次帶我們回到《舊約聖經》
回到哪裏?
回到《創世紀》裏面
回到《創世紀》
起初上帝按照祂的形象去做人
我們每一個人本有上帝完美聖潔的形象
但是因着我們的叛逆
因着我們的罪惡
我們隨從己意
我們損壞了我們生命裏面上帝的形象
然後我們追求地上
地上有很多的卡神
有很多的偶像
我們追求地上偶像的形象
於是耶穌最後那句
祂說什麼?
「該殺的歸該殺」
不要追求該殺的形象
上帝的歸上帝
要我們回到追求上帝的形象
如果你在基督徒
我們可以回到上帝的面前
我們可以重新備造上帝的形象
是因爲上帝的內子
上帝完美的形象
耶穌基督爲我們備毀贖罪
有沒有想過這件事?
上帝的兒子
耶穌基督是最靚仔的那個
而當你去到《二創亞書》五十三章
你看到耶穌的樣子
巴喊入目
因爲祂爲我們的緣故備毀容
爲我們贖罪
使我們今天在基督裏面
可以重新穿上上帝的形象
這個世界所追求的形象是
錢、性、力量
不外乎就是那些東西
金錢、情慾、權力
在耶穌基督裏面
我們追求的是錢、性、力量的另外一邊
我們追求的是GPS
Generosity
Purity
Submission
慷慨
聖潔
馴服
這是耶穌彰顯給我們看
天國是什麼一回事
接着去到第四個回合
復活的上帝
我不知道你還記不記得那個故事
很有趣的一個故事
耶穌怒罵撒都哥的人
但他用了很有技術、很有藝術的方式
一個前後呼應的結構去怒罵他們
接着在結構的中間
他帶我們回到出埃及記的荊棘天
他又是用舊約去啓示他真正的身份
他去啓示給我們看
你知道我是誰
我是那個更偉大、更完美的魔勢
我要帶領你們
經歷一個終極的出埃及
終極的出埃及
不是離開香港
是離開這個世界
這個罪惡的死地
進入上帝完美又占身的永恆天國
耶穌彰顯祂自己的使命
彰顯祂的身份
四輪緊張刺激的聖殿爭霸
四篇精彩絕倫的天國講道
一幅華麗壯觀的舊恩圖畫
你明不明白
你聽着四篇道,但其實你聽着一幅圖畫
他每一篇道
在畫圖畫的其中一邊
於是他想將整幅圖畫呈現在我們的面前
這幅圖畫很複雜
這幅圖畫很美麗
不過去到第五個回合又出了少少問題
有少少不同
甚至我可以說
你去到第五個回合的時候有少少失望
有一個文士來問耶穌什麼是最大的誡命
在誡命當中最大的是什麼
然後耶穌回答了要愛神愛人
大家聽過這些嗎
我覺得很簡單
沒錯,耶穌在回答當中
祂回答得很好,回答得很妙
到一個地步
連那個來試探他的文士
對耶穌佩服的萬分
甚至可以說
到故事的結局好像有少少化敵爲友
那個人來試探耶穌竟然好像想拜他爲師
然而耶穌的結局令我們有少少不滿
結局就是耶穌跟他說了一句話
你離上帝的國不遠了
那是怎樣呢
一個兩頭不到岸的說話
你離上帝的國不遠了
你不在上帝的國裏面
但是你又離開上帝的國
其實不是很遠
那下一步應該怎樣
我們怎樣纔可以進入上帝的國
如果有人跟你說
你離開上帝的國不遠
你不要走開
那是怎樣呢
那下一步我怎樣纔可以進入上帝的國
耶穌沒有說清楚的
在第五個回合裏面
耶穌這裏有一些叫做Unfinished Business
祂還有一些未搞定的事務
所以整個故事有個感覺是
To be continued
第五個回合是有上下集的
上集叫做最大的解密
下集是什麼
下集就是今天我要跟你講的叫做
大衛的後裔
最大的解密是上集,大衛的後裔是下集
當我們讀這個故事
你見到耶穌開口
給個難題,他們解不通
於是他們怕了耶穌走
當你讀耶穌第一次追擊去問問題的時候
我們很容易有個誤解
我們以爲當這個民事輸了離開的時候
耶穌仍然是怒髮衝冠
祂仍然很生氣,於是祂再次追問
祂將民事和祂的死黨
祂的那些同黨叫回來
問一個難題,他們解釋不了
於是要將他們置之死地
問到他們口啞啞
叫他們在當衆出醜
這個是我們通常想到的圖畫
但是真正的圖畫不是這樣
真正的圖畫是
耶穌想通過祂問的問題
他們答不到的問題
耶穌是在做什麼
耶穌其實是污底過身
去扶他們起身
耶穌其實通過祂在問的問題
是恩典呼召他們迴轉
耶穌想他們知道祂是誰
耶穌想他們知道進入天國的大門在哪裏
你記得那個民事
距離天國不遠
但是天國門在哪裏呢
天國在哪裏,怎麼可以進去呢
耶穌在第六個回合裏面
祂想告訴他們
這是我今天要講的故事
我先由《馬太福音》開始講
《馬太福音》有一個平衡的經文
我想從《馬太福音》的平衡經文入手
《馬太福音》平衡經文開始的時候這麼說
它說
法利塞人聚集的時候
如果你看回《馬太福音》之前第34節的時候
他們已經聚集
於是他們在聚集的過程裏面
他們派出了一個律法師去試探耶穌
現在去到7節之後
在41節裏面
他們又次再聚集一系
你猜這個故事繼續下去應該會是什麼樣子
這個故事繼續下去就是說
他們會又派出另外一個人
目的是要謀害耶穌
於是耶穌不讓他們有這樣的機會
於是耶穌先發制人
反問他們一個問題
耶穌問他們論到基督你們的意見如何
我想告訴你們耶穌不是怕了他們
所以先發制人
耶穌問這個問題
因爲耶穌不想他們持續的叛逆
以至罪孽深種無法回頭
你明不明
耶穌不是怕了他們
所以問這個問題
耶穌不想他們繼續想辦法去害他們
於是祂問他們一個問題
祂問他們什麼問題
祂說論到基督你們的意見如何
請留意耶穌沒有問什麼問題
耶穌沒有問你對今天的政治氣候怎樣看
耶穌沒有問你對香港下半年的展望怎樣看
你明不明
耶穌問他們什麼
耶穌問你覺得基督是如何
有沒有想過有些問題比其他你每天讀的問題都更重要
耶穌要他們思想最終極的問題論到基督你們的意見如何
耶穌要將光影帶回他們身上
不是因爲他們覺得自己很重要
而是因爲除非他們認識耶穌
除非你和我認識耶穌
我們沒有辦法得救
今天也是一樣
難得大家幾個月沒有回教會
現在可以回來
你猜我們今天在港臺要說些什麼
香港經歷了這麼多
接着明天又不知道會發生什麼事
下半年不知道會發生什麼事
你是否在等待牧師評論香港現在的走勢
接着跟你一起爲過去、爲現在、爲將來祈福呢
不是
我們要想的是論到基督你們的意見如何
令我想起一本書
一本已經超過十年的書
十年前
2009年在美國有一本書叫做《Christless Christianity》
《沒有基督的基督教》
這個作者在描述在美國教會里面發生的事
我不是在講社會
是在講教會里面發生的事
當教會的所謂基督徒開始想基督教是什麼
他再不是想基督是怎樣的一個救主
他就開始想一個基督教的文化應該是怎樣
於是我們所信的基督教變成了一種道德的教導
人生的哲學
做事的態度
做人的智慧
什麼是基督教
什麼是基督信仰
是道德嗎
是做人嗎
是哲學嗎
是智慧嗎
不
答案是不
基督教是關於基督的
所以今天你回來
我作爲你的牧師
哎呀
我要講什麼
我只可以講一樣東西
我必須要跟你講基督
因爲我的主耶穌
祂自己最喜歡和他們講耶穌
因爲唯有耶穌可以拯救他們
耶穌敢問
耶穌說
他是誰的後裔呢
他們說
問是
法利初人回答
是大衛的
是大衛的後裔
the son of David
大衛的後裔
對不對
答案是對的
非常對
兩隻手指都給了他
兩個like
在當時基本上所有的猶太人
你問他
你是否在等待猶太的基督來
你是否在等待彌撒爾來
大家都會說是
他是誰
他是大衛的兒子
是一個很好的答案
不過是一個不完全的答案
是一個不完整的答案
講得完
只是因爲這個答案其實未完整
於是耶穌將這個答案變成了一個難題
反向的
我帶你回到《馬爾福音》第十二章
第35、36節這樣講
耶穌在聖殿裏教導人
有很多其他人在聽耶穌的教導
問他們說
民事怎麼說基督是大衛的後裔呢
之前他在衆人面前問民事
你覺得基督是誰的兒子
於是民事說
當然是大衛的兒子
現在他轉向衆人
好像落他們的臉
你有沒有聽民事說
民事說基督是大衛的後裔
然後他再加一句說話
第十二章第36節
這個是引用《舊約聖經》的
他說你有沒有讀過《舊約聖經》
《舊約聖經》在詩篇第110篇裏面
大衛這麼說
大衛被聖靈感動說
主對我主說
如果你回去看《希伯來文》
其實很清楚
主是壓回
耶和華對我,我是誰,我是大衛
我主,我的主是誰
是那個基督,是那個彌賽亞,是那個君王
耶和華對我大衛的主基督
這樣說
當大衛叫基督做主的時候
問題就出現了
因爲對於猶太人來說
那個排行是很重要的
如果一個基督是大衛的兒孫
他沒有理由是高於他
但是爲什麼他既是他的兒孫
他又會叫他做主呢
不合理的
於是耶穌反問他們
祂說你繼續讀下去
你坐在我的右邊
讓我把你的仇敵放在你一腳下
這也是在引用《司篇》第110篇第一節
於是到耶穌講了
第12章第37節
他引用了舊約
他說大衛親自稱他爲主
他怎麼又是大衛的後裔呢
怎麼可能
一方面是他的老闆
另一方面是他的後輩
我知道在現在我們的世界裏面
是沒有辦法明白的
可能我們當中的小朋友
當然你做爸爸
都是想他比你厲害
可能你在某家公司裏面打工
結果你的兒子竟然做了老闆
這樣也可以的
那麼他又是你的兒子
又是你的老闆
行不行呢
是的
但是在舊時的世界裏面
在這個輩分分明的世界裏面
是不可能的事情
於是耶穌用這樣的情況
問了一個問題
他們回答不了
爲什麼他們回答不了
因爲以色列人
猶太人一直假設了一件事
基督是一個地上的光芒
如果他是在人類世界裏面
大衛的後裔永遠都是低於大衛的
他沒辦法想象
大衛生了個兒子
兒子竟然有一天可以和大衛說
我厲害過你
不行的
老祖宗
你怎麼可能比老祖宗厲害呢
我們說
我們怎麼解決這個難題
怎麼可以解決
基督又是大衛的兒子
又是大衛的boss
他的主
答案其實
馬可早就給了我們
答案在哪裏
馬可給了個答案
我們在馬可福音第一章第一節
但是可能你兩年多前
你在這裏
聽我講這篇道理就知道了
馬可福音第一章第一節怎麼講
他說上帝的兒子
耶穌基督福音的起頭
如果你看他原文
那些次序是調轉了的
原文的次序是怎樣呢
起頭
福音的起頭
耶穌基督福音的起頭
上帝的兒子
馬可在第一章第一節
已經給你攤牌
告訴你耶穌是誰
耶穌不是大衛之子
這麼簡單
不是不對
但是耶穌最終極的是誰
他是上帝的兒子
從人的角度裏面
他是通過大衛出來
於是大衛可以說
這個是我的後裔
但是從另外一個角度裏面
他是從上帝那裏出來的
於是大衛只可以
俯首稱臣
說你是我的主
馬可一早就給了答案我們
不過那羣發理菜人
那羣民事不知道
是不是
更準確的
他們不是不知道
他們是不願意接受
爲什麼這麼說呢
因爲如果之前你有留意第一個回合
外子的權柄裏面
耶穌已經提了
你聽不聽到那把聲音
這是我的外子
我纔是原的
耶穌是誰
你有沒有聽到天上那把聲音
這是我的外子
在邪惡的緣故里面
耶穌說
原主還有一個外子
真的是畫公仔畫出場
耶穌已經彰顯地告訴他真正的身份
他們不是聽不明白
他們是不願意接受
他們沒辦法接受這件事
於是他們沒辦法回答耶穌的問題
於是結局就是這樣
《馬達福音》第22章第46節
沒有一個人能回答
因爲他們不想接受耶穌是上帝的兒子
從那天以後沒有人敢再問他什麼
於是耶穌又再次擊敗了強敵
他又贏了
但我們要問一個問題
在這個回合裏面
他除了贏了之後
他有沒有通過他的對話
你記不記得
剛纔林穆斯說耶穌的回答永遠
一方面是擊退敵人
另一方面是解禁
另一方面是藉着他的對話
雖然這裏只有兩節聖經
啓示天國
耶穌通過他的說話
將上帝的拯救計劃
一步一步一層一層的展示給我們聽
耶穌有沒有解禁
有沒有再告訴我們
上帝的計劃是什麼
上帝的天文未入的答案是有的
他通過些什麼
去告訴我們更多關於天國的事
他通過一個經文
那個經文叫做《詩篇110篇》
《詩篇110篇》
爲什麼這個詩篇重要
因爲這個詩篇是
新約聖經裏面引用得最多的詩篇
我知道我們不是很習慣去這樣想聖經
我們通常看金句
你最喜歡的金句是什麼
不是的
對於猶太人來說
他們覺得最重要的是什麼
哪一節聖經是引用在新約最多的
那個不就是最重要的了
在新約聖經裏面
引用得最多的舊約徵節是什麼
是《詩篇110篇》第一節
如果你看到這個紀錄
就要告訴你
在很多本書裏面都有引用過《詩篇110篇》
而聖經學者告訴你
《詩篇110篇》的第一節
他數過在新約聖經裏面
明隱暗隱有25次或者以上
超大把《詩篇110篇》
耶穌帶我們回到《詩篇110篇》
祂說你想不想知道我是誰
如果你想知道我是誰
我要帶你回到《詩篇110篇》
《詩篇110篇》第一節這麼說
耶穌說對我主說
你坐在我的右邊
我使你仇敵坐你的腳凳
第二節
耶穌說必使你從塞安伸出你能力的權柄
你要務要在仇敵中掌權
第一 祂說你坐在我的右邊
什麼叫我的右邊
我的右邊是權能的位置
現在人一聽就知道了
哇 坐在我的右邊
耶和華的右邊
這個基督是在上帝耶和華的右邊
當你看這兩節《詩篇》
我問你《詩篇110篇》是關於什麼的
是一個怎樣類型的詩篇
你讀過主義學你都知道
馬上舉手說
牧師我知道是君王的詩篇
是君王的詩篇
是關於一個君王的詩篇
但還沒完
還有
當你繼續讀下去
去到第四節的時候就很有趣了
在第四節的時候
你會發現這個君王突然間穿起了一個
不是龍袍
是祭司袍
所以我要你想象一下
他穿着袍
戴着冠冕
他穿着袍一看就知道是君王的袍
但我想你想象
他其實不是穿着龍袍
這個君王穿着
咦 祭司袍
是罪衣來的
都不夠威的
爲何會穿着祭司袍出來
卻是一個這樣的呈現上帝的天國
我想和你一起讀
《詩篇110》第四節
耶和華起了誓
絕不改變
是照着默基洗德的體系
永遠作祭司
你照着默基洗德的體系
耶穌是猶大的支派
耶穌其實不應該是可以做到祭司的
因爲唯有利美才是
但這部詩篇所講的是
上帝在祂的計劃當中
將來有另外一個體系會出來
那體系不是出於地上的體系
那體系不是出於利美的體系
那體系是出於默基洗德的體系
你知不知道誰叫默基洗德
有沒有聽過這個名
是不是很酷呢
都要記一記這個名
這個名
默基洗德在整本《聖經》裏面出現過三次
在頭、在中、在尾
你可能會說請我告訴他
林洛斯有那麼多東西要學
我怎麼會學這些東西呢
對以色列人來說很重要
你不懂默基洗德
你整本《希伯來書》
你都不知道在發生什麼事
第一次出現
默基洗德在《創世紀》第十四章
然後在《詩篇110》
最後
《希伯來書》的第七章
默基洗德是什麼
默基洗德是耶穌基督的影子
如果你有機會回去看《希伯來書》第七章
很酷的
我很喜歡
就是我不懂的時候
我都覺得很酷的一句話
默基洗德第三節這麼說
他無父無母
無族譜
無生之恥
無命之重是與上帝的兒子相似
他永遠作祭祀
無父無母
無家譜
無始無終
是不是很有意思
有些人覺得
這是上帝耶穌在舊約裏面的出現
但是我想一個更正確的看法
也是學者大部分的看法
他其實是一個普通人
不過在《創世紀》裏面
這個人沒有記載他有父母
沒有記載他有家族
而你知道《創世紀》是怎樣的一本書
充滿族譜的書
爲什麼《創世紀》是充滿族譜的書
是因爲我告訴你
有始有終
每一個人都會死
如果阿當、阿娃沒有犯罪的時候
有沒有族譜這件事
有
不過族譜是越來越加名
沒有減名的
你知道我們教會有個會員名單
有個會友的名冊
我們會友的名冊有家
是不是
下個星期有人加入教會了
有
有沒有減
因爲他會死
在《創世紀》裏面的族譜
有家有減有始有終
告訴你每個人都會死
不過默基西德在舊約聖經裏面
沒有在族譜裏面
無父無母無始無終
他成爲一個影子指向耶穌基督
無始無終的大祭祀
去到第五節
繼續
「在你右邊的主
當祂發怒的日子必打傷列王」
第六節
「祂要審判列國
施首就豐滿
祂要痛擊遍地的領袖」
這就差不多完了
我想你留意一件事
你有沒有留意到
《詩篇》110篇很可愛
其實是一個三文字
是一個三文字
《詩篇》118篇的第一節至第三節
是講耶穌是君王
耶穌是君王
然後去到第五節至第七節
也有祂做回君王
但是中間夾了一節
就是第四節
「而我起了誓」
這個君王是怎樣的
「要照着默基使得的體系永遠作祭祀」
這個君王又是祭祀
這是耶穌想啓示的東西
祂說:你知道我是誰嗎?
我是聖潔公義的君王
你知道我來做什麼嗎?
我來審判你
我來審判萬國
也帶那羣人回到《詩篇》110篇
如果你知道有一個人是聖潔公義的君王
他又是審判萬國的君王
你會怎樣呢?
你會說:我和他做朋友
是因爲你不知道你自己周身事
你以爲你是gentleman child
周身事
其實你滿身都是事
如果你知道這個世界有一個君王
他是聖潔公義
他會審判萬國
你頂籠是敬而遠之
心存懼怕
你明不明白?
你去不到靠近他
你敢不敢靠近他?
因爲他將要審判你的罪惡
然而耶穌不單止是那個君王
他也是憐憫罪人的祭祀
他是永活爲我們祈求的祭祀
於是
在《希伯來書》的時候
祂說:我們可以坦然無懼來到祂的寶座前
我們怎麼可能來到祂的寶座前
我們怎麼可以坦然無懼
是因爲祂不單止是君王
祂不單止是審判者
祂也是憐憫者
祂是我們的大祭祀
沒有這個三文治
沒有這個漢武包
我們沒有辦法被拯救
耶穌是君王
然而祂也是我們良善的祭祀
令我想起C.S. Lewis在《Corneliania》裏面
那個很精彩的故事
大家都大概有個印象
講到這個兒童的故事裏面的獅子
獅子王其實是耶穌的一個影像
當中有一個很精彩的對話
他這麼說,一羣小孩聽聞獅子王阿斯蘭的一個對話
"Is he a man?" asked Lucy
"Is Aslan a man?" said Mr. Beaver sternly
"Certainly not, I tell you he is the king of the wood
he is the son of the great emperor beyond the sea
Don't you know who is the king of the beast?
Aslan is a lion, the lion, the great lion"
Lucy有個小孩問,他說
"Is he a man?" asked Aslan
"Is Aslan a man?"
海里先生很嚴肅的回答
"Certainly not, I tell you he is the king of the wood
he is the son of the great emperor beyond the sea
Don't you know who is the king of the beast?
Aslan is a lion, the lion, the great lion"
於是他繼續
"Oh!" said Susan
"I thought he was a man, is he quite safe?
I shall feel rather nervous about meeting a lion"
"That you will, dearie, and make no mistake" said Mrs. Beaver
"If there is anyone who can appear before Aslan
without their knees knocking
they are either braver than most
or else just silly"
"Oh!" Susan 繼續問
"I thought Aslan was a man, is he quite safe?
I shall feel rather nervous about meeting a lion"
"That you will, dearie, and make no mistake
If there is anyone who can appear before Aslan
without their knees knocking
they are either braver than most
or else just silly"
"Then he isn't safe" said Lucy
"Safe?" said Mr. Beaver
"Don't you hear what Mrs. Beaver tells you?
Who said anything about safe?
'Cause he isn't safe
But he's good
He's a king
But he's good, I tell you"
"Then he isn't safe" said Lucy
"Safe?" said Mr. Beaver
"Don't you hear what Mrs. Beaver tells you?
Who said anything about safe?
'Cause he isn't safe
When you see Aslan"
"He's a good man
He's a king
He's a safe king
He's a good king"
In this story, do you know
how Aslan showed his good side at the end?
He sacrificed his own life for one of his children.
When you return to the Bible,
where does Jesus' good side show?
It shows that he sacrificed his life for a sinner like you and me.
I'd like to take you to the first chapter of Hebrews.
The first chapter of Hebrews is a story
about how the king became a priest.
The first chapter of Hebrews,
the third chapter.
It's only one chapter.
"He is the glorious light of God.
He is the true image of God.
He used His mighty commandment to hold all people."
Then, the second half of the verse.
"He cleansed the sins of men.
He sat on the right hand of God."
The author of Hebrews only used one chapter of the Bible
to summarize Jesus' life.
Jesus' head descended from heaven.
He is the glorious light of God.
He is the true image of God.
Where was he originally?
He was not born in Hong Kong.
He was not born in Paris.
He was not born.
He is the glorious light of God.
He used His mighty commandment to hold all people.
This is the first half of Jesus' life.
"But for our sake, He rose up as a man."
Not only did He rise up as a man,
but He also became the Savior who was nailed to the cross.
"He cleansed the sins of men.
He sat on the right hand of God."
Here, He skipped very quickly.
His first half of life descended from heaven.
His second half of life ascended from heaven.
When He ascended the cross, He did not die.
He resurrected.
After He resurrected, He ascended to heaven.
Where is He now?
He is now sitting on the right hand of the Almighty.
I tell you, the author of the book of Hebrews
loved the 110 chapters of the book of Hebrews.
He loved it so much that he quoted the first chapter five times.
We can say that the whole book of Hebrews
was written based on the 110 chapters of the book of Hebrews.
This is the first time he quoted the 110 chapters of the book of Hebrews.
He reminds us where Jesus is now.
He tells us that Jesus is now on the highest heaven.
He tells us where Jesus is now.
He is on the right hand of God.
On the highest heaven, on the right hand of God.
Not only that,
but He also reminds us of another thing.
He says, "Look at Jesus.
He is not standing there.
He is sitting there."
What's the difference?
If He is tired, He can just sit there.
No.
He has already achieved His salvation,
so He can sit there.
The author of the book of Hebrews tells us,
"You have to pay attention to where Jesus is.
You have to pay attention to the position of Jesus' body.
The position of Jesus and the position of His body
is a great expectation for us Christians."
What kind of expectation?
In the 10th chapter of the book of Hebrews,
the 11th chapter,
this is the expectation of us Christians.
All the priests are standing there every day to serve God.
Can you see what the priests are doing?
They are standing there.
Why?
No matter how they serve God,
no matter how they kill the animals,
they can't get rid of their sins.
They are standing there to serve God.
And also,
like the workers in Amazon,
and also,
they can't sit still.
"They are offering the same offering over and over again.
This offering can never be removed."
But what about Jesus?
"But Jesus offered an ever-valuable offering."
What is He now?
He is not standing there.
He is sitting there.
He is sitting on the right side of God.
Jesus is sitting there.
He is telling us that this is the expectation of Christians.
What is the expectation of Christians?
To be saved from sin,
to be faithful to God,
to be in harmony with God,
to be God's offspring,
to enter heaven,
and to have eternal life.
These are the expectations of Christians.
Jesus is now sitting on the right side of God.
He is giving us these expectations.
Nothing else is the expectation of Christians.
The expectation of Christians
is to start everything from the highest level.
You know that recently,
because of my wife's illness,
I went to a lot of different doctors with her.
Yesterday, I went to a doctor's clinic.
While I was waiting,
I was curious and looked around to see what was going on.
This doctor was great.
A lot of patients
were cured by him.
So I gave him a lot of gifts,
a lot of souvenirs.
So I looked around to see what was written on the gifts.
"Miracle of the heart"
"Forever in the world"
"Long live the Church"
These are the gifts.
But I was thinking,
if one day you go to a doctor's clinic,
and you see that this doctor has a lot of souvenirs,
a lot of people give him gifts,
but the words written on the gifts are
"Eye-catching"
"Turning the world upside down"
"Gold-plated"
Do you think it's strange?
Did I go to the wrong place?
Or did the person who gave the gifts
misremembered a souvenir?
If you look at it again,
it says "Long-lasting"
"God's will"
"Turning the world upside down"
Do you think it's too much?
Is this really a doctor?
Or is this the Virgin Mary?
I want to ask you something.
If you have received Jesus' grace,
and you have a strong desire for Jesus,
and now you want to give Jesus a gift,
give Jesus a souvenir,
what will you write?
Do you understand what I mean?
A lot of us misunderstand
and don't know who Jesus is.
So, we thank Jesus for guarding people's hearts.
We thank Jesus for financial wealth.
We thank Jesus for the end of the world.
It's crazy!
It's all wrong!
Jesus' real gift to us is
"to drink, to eat, to sleep, to be obedient, to be pure, to be in harmony with God,
to be God's children,
to enter God's heaven,
and to be God's descendants forever."
This is the most precious thing in the Bible.
The people written in the Bible
have a very miserable life.
They are under great pressure.
He didn't tell them
that the only hope we have is that God can save us
from this misery.
He pointed to their only hope,
their sin, to save their lives.
Why can Jesus save our sins?
Because he said in chapter 9,
"For there is no image of the real church in the Bible,
the image of the real church,
the church on earth."
So, you remember,
he kept reminding you where Jesus is.
Jesus is in heaven.
Jesus is not on earth.
If Jesus is buried on earth,
if there is no resurrection, if there is no ascension,
can Jesus save us?
He can't.
Why can Jesus save us?
Because he is in heaven now.
He has entered heaven.
He is not a man-made saint,
but he has entered heaven,
appeared before God,
and offered himself to the Lord only once
to atone for his sins.
Jesus is in heaven.
This is very important.
If he offered himself to God on earth, it would be useless.
He must be in heaven,
on the right side of God in heaven.
He offered himself to God.
Hebrews chapter 8, verse 1,
"For we have such a great master."
He is already in heaven.
He is not standing, but sitting.
"He is sitting on the right side of heaven,
in the church."
The church is not the church on earth.
"For the truth is not the truth, but the truth is the truth of the Lord,
and not of man."
Who is Jesus?
He is in heaven.
What is Jesus doing?
He is sitting there.
He has completed all his salvation.
So, let me tell you,
the age of our church is less than a century.
What I said this week is very reasonable.
Because on Thursday,
something happened,
which is our Ascension Day.
But there is no Ascension Day in our church.
You have been in church for so long,
or the Hong Kong government gives you a holiday.
Every time you go, it is Christmas,
Good Friday,
Lent,
and Resurrection Day.
Will the government give you an Ascension Day?
We should have a request.
The government must give me an Ascension Day.
Otherwise, our salvation is not complete.
The government does not understand our Christian faith.
There are four things in our Christian faith, which must be done.
We should not let go of Friday,
but we should let go of Ascension Day.
Jesus came down from heaven.
He is the representative of the Holy Spirit.
He came to all of us.
He cried out to us,
"The end of the world is near. You should repent."
He did not cry out to us,
"Follow me as a human being.
Follow my wisdom of life.
I will teach you how to be a good person."
No, no.
He said, "The end of the world is near. You should repent."
Then he went up the cross for us,
and went out of the tomb for us.
He left the world.
He ascended.
He is the representative of repentance.
When he ascended to heaven,
he represented us.
Why did he pray to God?
It is like a country that has been translated.
He came to a big country to pray.
What do you have to do when you pray?
You need a gift.
What is Jesus' gift?
It is himself.
Jesus' gift is his blood.
Jesus' gift is his perfect and unsullied baptism.
He is not only a Baptist,
he is also a Christian.
So Jesus rose from the dead.
He was crucified.
He was resurrected.
He ascended to heaven.
Jesus' four great missions are inseparable.
In fact, there is one more.
Are the five great missions better?
It is true that the five great missions are inseparable.
Jesus has one more mission at the end.
He will come back to judge the world.
This is what is said in the Bible.
He is the King of Kings.
The King of Kings will come back to judge the world.
Jesus will definitely come back.
He was crucified.
He ascended to heaven.
He was resurrected.
He will come back.
One day, he will stand up again.
He will not sit there anymore.
He will come back.
He will judge every sinner in this world.
Are you ready?
Do you know who Jesus is?
When Jesus comes to judge you,
can you bear it?
Let me tell you.
There is one person who is not ready.
That person is the priest.
So Jesus said to him,
"You are not welcome in the kingdom of God."
"You are not in the kingdom of God."
Why?
Because this person is a fool.
He asked Jesus,
"What is the main point of the Law?"
Jesus said to him, "To love God and to love people."
He said, "OK, OK, to love God and to love people."
"I will no longer be involved in these useless things."
"I will go out and be a good person."
"I want to love God. I want to love people."
"I want to serve my community."
He thought he was very wise.
So Jesus answered him,
"You are not welcome in the kingdom of God."
Jesus said to him,
"You don't know me at all."
"You don't know that you are not in the kingdom of God."
"You cannot enter the kingdom of God."
Why?
Because for this person,
Jesus was only a good teacher.
Jesus was not a Savior.
So at the end, I would like to ask you.
I would like to ask you.
I would like to ask you a very important question
through our last episode.
Not only do you need to know what the answer is,
but you also need to believe wholeheartedly.
What is the core of Christianity?
If today someone examines you,
what is the core of Christianity?
The core of Christianity?
You may have been in the church for a long time.
You may have been in the synagogue for a long time.
Or you may have been in another church for a long time.
I would like to ask you.
What is the core of Christianity?
Choose one.
Is it A or 1?
"Follow Christ and love God and love people."
Very attractive.
Or is it E or B?
Have you heard of it?
It is a golden rule.
"People treat you, and you treat people."
Do you believe it?
At that time, some laymen answered this question.
They said, "What is the core of the whole law?"
"People treat you, and you treat people."
Or is it C or B?
"Leadership is more blessed."
These are all the words you learned when you were young.
What is the core of Christianity?
1, 2, or 3?
You said, "Pastor Lam, it is difficult to choose."
"Everyone wants to choose."
"Everyone is like this."
"It doesn't matter. I will give you the 4th one."
"All of the above."
Is it right?
It must be right.
"All of the above."
The answer is not "All of the above."
It is "None of the above."
It is completely wrong.
If you choose one of them, or choose the 4th one,
you are completely wrong.
Why?
Because that is not the core of our faith.
The core of our faith is
how you view Christ.
Who is Christ?
This is the core of our faith.
Two weeks ago,
when I was preparing for my English class,
I thought of a book.
It is called "In His Steps."
This book is very old.
It was written in 1896.
But there are new versions of it.
Recently, it is still airing on TV.
"In His Steps" is about
a group of people
who have a Sunday evening
in a small church town.
Suddenly, they feel moved.
"Why don't we start from this week?"
"Let us see our disciples."
"Let us serve them like Jesus."
"Let us see how God will glorify Himself."
So, the story begins.
This is a false story.
I don't mean it to be false.
I mean it is fictional.
It is created by God Himself.
In this story,
many people start to influence other people's lives.
It is like Jesus.
When Jesus saw this scripture,
He did what He had to do.
So, the whole town is completely different.
It is completely different after a week.
This story becomes the Christian faith of many people.
Have you ever heard of it?
"What will Jesus do?"
What will Jesus do?
One of the most important principles.
When you see a person,
whether it is on the street or at home,
you see a person who does not like his brother,
but his brother likes him,
and when his brother hurts his brother,
you say, "What will Jesus do?"
Right?
You think this is a very good principle.
Think about how Jesus will treat your brother.
How will Jesus treat your brother?
This becomes our principle.
But have you noticed one thing?
"What will Jesus do?"
It covers the cross of Jesus.
It is gone.
We can only see Jesus as a teacher.
Jesus as a teacher.
But we can't see the tomb of Jesus.
We can't see his cross.
We can't see his sanctification.
We can't see his crucifixion.
We can't see "He will come again."
What is the core of Christian faith?
It is the dead king,
the ever-living teacher.
Or the other Jesus
who has shown himself,
is the risen, dead, resurrected, sanctified,
who will come again to judge the world.
This is the echo we want to convey.
Where is Jesus today?
He is sitting on the right hand of God.
He has taken over the world.
He is sitting here.
He has atoned for us.
There is no other Savior in this world.
I want to ask you.
I'm not asking you if you have the scent of Christ.
Sometimes we like to ask,
the Christian Church likes to ask,
"Do you have the scent of Christ?"
What does that mean?
Do you have the scent of Christ?
This is an important question,
but it is a secondary question.
Do you believe in Jesus?
Do you know that he is the only Savior
who has risen, died, resurrected,
and sat on the right hand of God for us?
At the end of the sermon,
I want to give you two chapters of the Bible,
the description of Hebrews.
Hebrews said,
"Do you know where Jesus is?
He is sitting on the right hand of God."
This is the first chapter of Hebrews chapter 5,
verse 110.
Hebrews said,
"Therefore, since we have so many witnesses
who are like clouds surrounding us,
we should cast down all kinds of heavy burdens,
and do what is most necessary,
and a firm heart
shall not be put in our way."
Brothers and sisters,
dear friends,
I want to ask you,
do you have any burdens?
Do you have any sins?
Do you know the background of Hebrews?
Why does Hebrews write this book?
Why does he write 13 chapters?
Because there are many Catholics
who are leaving the Church in Rome.
Why are they leaving the Church?
It is because of the power of the Holy Spirit,
because of the power of the world,
because of the hardship of life,
because of the pressure of faith.
We do not have the pressure of faith yet,
but we seem to have it very soon.
But we have both in front of us.
We have the power of the world,
and we have the hardship of life.
Many people say,
"Jesus is like this.
He does not expect much from me."
So they leave the Church.
Hebrews writes this book to tell you,
"Think no more.
You are gone.
Because otherwise there is no salvation,
there is no other Jesus in heaven."
How do you face your sin?
When God comes back to judge you,
how can you enter His kingdom?
Never leave.
So He encourages them to endure to the end,
and to cast aside the confusion of this world,
the sins that haunt them.
The last verse says,
"Look up to our faith,
and be like the Lord Jesus."
Where is He?
"He wears the joy of being in front of you,
the lightness, the glory,
and the endurance of the cross."
Where is He in the cross?
"And now He sits on the right hand of the Lord."
You need to know Jesus.
What did He do in all that He did?
He died for us.
He rose from the dead for us.
He resurrected for us.
Where is He now?
He is the Savior.
There is no salvation without Him.
Do you believe that?
Look up to Him.
Follow Him.
Follow the way of Heaven.
This is what God has called us to do.
May we listen to His call,
and respond to His call.
This is our prayer.
Our Heavenly Father,
we truly thank you.
Because in the Last Supper,
we not only remember David's son,
or his descendant.
He was also the son of God.
But we thank you
not because of these questions.
Who is Jesus?
Yes, I know.
The whole gospel is about His resurrection,
His death, resurrection, and resurrection.
We are in a very vague world.
We do not know
what is the true faith of Christ.
There is no difference between us and the world.
So when we come to church,
we are worried about the current pandemic,
the difficulties in life,
and the fear of the future.
So we look forward to
being able to talk about these things in church.
On the contrary,
when we look at the early church,
they point us to another world,
where we can see Jesus Christ, who is victorious for us,
sitting on the right hand of God's power.
He is the only Savior.
So we have to endure,
we have to persist,
in this world,
in this short life,
to be a witness for you,
to ask you to help us,
to become a church like this,
to follow Jesus,
to be a witness for His light.
We pray in this way,
in the name of Jesus Christ.
安保